<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle to all professors in New-England, Germany, and other parts of the called Christian vvorld also to the Jews and Turks throughout the world, that they may see who are the true worshippers of God, that He seeks, and in what He is worshipped ... / George Fox.</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40173</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1806</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16139</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11851107</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11851107</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49932</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40173)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49932)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 29:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle to all professors in New-England, Germany, and other parts of the called Christian vvorld also to the Jews and Turks throughout the world, that they may see who are the true worshippers of God, that He seeks, and in what He is worshipped ... / George Fox.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Library of Congress.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Correspondence.</term>
               <term>God --  Worship and love.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49932:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49932:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EPISTLE To all PROFESSORS IN <hi>New-England, Germany,</hi> and other Parts of the called Chriſtian VVorld.</p>
            <p>Alſo To the <hi>JEWS</hi> and <hi>TURKS</hi> throughout the WORLD.</p>
            <p>That they may ſee who are the true Worſhippers of God, that he ſeeks, and in what he is worſhipped.</p>
            <p>An Exhortation to them to read it over, that they may ſee what they have all grieved, vext and quenched, and what they have walked deſpightfully, and rebelled, and kickt, and ſtopt their Ears, and cloſed their Eyes to; ſo that they may all return again, and turn within, and ſee what they have <hi>profeſt,</hi> and <hi>not poſſeſt;</hi> ſo that they may come to be the tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors of the Truth, and true Worſhippers in the Spirit of the True and Living God, who is a Spirit, which is the perfect Worſhip, which Chriſt the Truth and perfect One ſet up above 1600 Years ſince.</p>
            <p>George Fox.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:49932:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49932:2"/>
            <head>AN EPISTLE To all Profeſſors in <hi>New-England, Germany,</hi> and other Parts of the called CHRISTIAN WORLD. Concerning the Worſhip of God, which Chriſt ſet up above 1600 Years ſince, as in <hi>John</hi> 4.</head>
            <p>WHen the Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> ſaid unto Chriſt, <hi>Our Fathers worſhipped God in this Mountain,</hi> which was the Mountain where <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Well was; and ſaid ſhe again, <hi>you ſay that at</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem <hi>is the Place where Men ought to worſhip;</hi> but Jeſus ſaid unto her, <hi>Woman, believe me, the Hour cometh when ye ſhall neither at this Mountain, nor yet at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>worſhip the Father; Ye worſhip ye know not what, we know what we worſhip, for Salvation is of the</hi> Jews; <hi>but the Hour cometh and now is, when the true Worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in Spirit and Truth, for the Father ſeeks ſuch to worſhip him; God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him muſt worſhip him in the Spirit and the Truth.</hi> Now mark this all Men and Women that are called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> or <hi>Jews,</hi> or <hi>Turks,</hi> or others, and ſee if you know what you worſhip, for there are many Worſhips in the World made and ſet up by Men, and ſo Men and Women worſhip they don't
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49932:3"/>
know what, that do not worſhip God in Spirit and Truth, as Chriſt ſaith; Now you may ſee there was a Worſhip at the Mountain where <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Well was, and alſo there was a Worſhip at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> at the Temple, ſet up many Years after <hi>Jacob</hi> dyed in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> by the <hi>Jews</hi> his Children, by the Command of God, and the Plague and the Puniſhment that was to come upon them that would not go up to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and keep the Feaſt of Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles, and to worſhip there from Year to Year, you may read <hi>Zechariah</hi> the 14th. And in the <hi>Acts</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>there was in</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>out of every Nation under Heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 2.</note> 
               <hi>which worſhipped at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>in the time of</hi> Penti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſt, <hi>many of many ſtrange Languages and Tongues, and were amazed at the Apoſtles that preacht Chriſt:</hi> Now in <hi>John</hi> the 4th, there you may ſee how that Jeſus Chriſt put down the Worſhip at the Mountain where <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Well was, where the Fore-Fathers worſhipt, and alſo put down the VVorſhip at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where the <hi>Jews,</hi> the latter Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers worſhipt, and where they came out of other Parts to worſhip, and if they did not, the Lord poured his Plagues and Judgments upon them, as in <hi>Zechariah</hi> the 14th; now when Chriſt put down theſe two Worſhips, at the Mountain where <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Well was, and at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he ſet up another Worſhip in the Spirit and in the Truth, and ſaid, <hi>ſuch the Father ſeeks to worſhip him;</hi> and that Hour that he put down theſe two Worſhips at the Mountain and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the ſame Hour he ſet up a Worſhip; for his Words are, <hi>not at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>nor at this</hi> Mountain <hi>ſhall ye worſhip the Father, believe me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt: So they that hold up a Worſhip at that Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain or at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> or a Worſhip of their own ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, worſhip they don't know what, and do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in Chriſt; for Chriſt's VVords are, <hi>Woman, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49932:3"/>
me,</hi> mark, <hi>the Hour cometh, when ye ſhall neither in this</hi> Mountain, <hi>nor yet at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>worſhip the Father, for ye worſhip ye know not what.</hi> So here it is clear, neither at the Mountain nor at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is the Father worſhipped; for Chriſt Jeſus has put down thoſe Worſhips, yea, at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which was once commanded of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe that God never commanded cannot ſtand; and Chriſts VVords are, <hi>But the Hour cometh and now is,</hi> mark (now is) then it began, that Hour when he put down the VVorſhip at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the Mountain, and ſuch VVorſhippers that did not know what they worſhipt; <hi>But the Hour cometh and now is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>when the true Worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in the Spirit and in the Truth, for the Father ſeeks ſuch to worſhip him; for God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him muſt worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth:</hi> now mark, all People upon the Earth, VVorſhippers of all Sorts, who worſhip you don't know what, that be out of this true VVorſhip; here you may ſee that Chriſt ſet up a VVorſhip, and its above 1600 Years ſince it began; and here you may ſee who the true VVorſhippers are, that worſhip the Father in the Spirit and in the Truth; and here you may ſee who they are the Father ſeeks to worſhip him, ſuch as be in the Spirit and ſuch as be in the Truth. So its clear that none are the true VVorſhippers of the Father, but who be in the Truth that the Devil is out of, for the Devil abode not in it. 2ly. None are the true Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of the Father but ſuch as are in the Spirit; yea, in that Spirit that mortifies Sin, and that Spirit by which the Body of Death and the Sins of the Fleſh are put of; ſo its clear all that be out of the Spirit and out of the Truth are the falſe Worſhippers, and not the true, and ſuch the Father ſeeks not to worſhip him; for God
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49932:4"/>
is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him muſt (mark) wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him in the Spirit, and in the Truth; for God is a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and he is the God of Truth that changeth not; and therefore every Man and every Woman muſt come to Truth in their Inward Parts, and come to the Spirit of God in their own particulars, and not grieve it, nor quench it, nor vex it; for in the Spirit and in the Truth they muſt worſhip the God of Truth, and God who is a Spirit: and mark, all Men and Women muſt be in the Spirit and in the Truth, if they worſhip the God of Truth in the Spirit and in the Truth; and this Worſhip that Chriſt Jeſus ſet up above 1600 Years ſince, breaks down all the Worſhips in the whole VVorld that Men have ſet up; and the <hi>Jew</hi>'s, and the Beaſt's, and the Dragon's that are out of Truth and the Spirit of God; ſo every Man and VVoman in the whole VVorld muſt come to Truth in their Inward Parts, by which Truth they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from Chriſt the Truth, in which Truth they muſt worſhip the God of Truth; and every Man and VVoman in the VVorld muſt come to the Spirit of God in their Hearts, by which Spirit they muſt have an Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to know God, who is a Spirit, and ſo to worſhip him in the Spirit: now there is the worſhipping of Angels, the will-worſhip, the VVorſhip that was at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the VVorſhip in the Mountain, the VVorſhip of the Beaſt and the Dragon, the VVorſhips that Men and all Nations have invented; but the VVorſhip in the Spirit and the Truth, which Chriſt ſet up above 1600 Years ſince, is the true VVorſhip which the Father ſeeks. So I ſay, this VVorſhip that Chriſt ſet up in the Spirit and in the Truth, and the true VVorſhippers that worſhip in it, that the Father ſeeks, are ſet above all the VVill-worſhippers, the VVorſhippers of Angels,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49932:4"/>
and the Worſhippers of the Beaſt and of the Dragon, and above the Worſhip at the Mountain, and <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Well, and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> Worſhip, and all the Worſhips that Men or Nations have invented; ſo every Man or Woman in the whole World muſt come to the Spirit of God and to the Truth, which comes from Chriſt in their Inward Parts, if they be the true Worſhippers that worſhip God in the Spirit and Truth, or to be ſuch as he ſeeks to worſhip him; for God is a Spirit, and he is the God of Truth, and therefore they muſt be all in the Spirit and in the Truth, if they be the true Worſhippers, and do worſhip God, the God of Truth, who is a Spirit, for ſuch he ſeeks; and all that be out of the Spirit they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip they don't know what, and he ſeeks not ſuch, and they are not the true Worſhippers; and there are all the <hi>Sects,</hi> and ſuch as grieves and quenches the Spirit, and comes not to the Truth in their Inward Parts, and ſuch as ſtop their Ears, and cloſe their Eyes to that of God in them, like the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and kicks againſt that which pricks them, like <hi>Saul,</hi> and ſuch as hates the true Light that enlightens every one that comes into the World, and walks deſpightfully againſt the Spirit of Grace, and ſuch as rebels againſt God's Spirit that is given unto them to inſtruct them, and to profit withall, <hi>Neh.</hi> 9. all ſuch worſhip not God in the Spirit and Truth, <hi>but they worſhip they know not what,</hi> as Chriſt ſaith; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt every Man and Woman in the whole World come to the True Light of Chriſt, and the Spirit, and the Grace in themſelves, if they be the true Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of God in Spirit and Truth.</p>
            <p>And the Worſhip that Chriſt Jeſus, the Heavenly Man, the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> the Lord from Heaven, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Man, ſet up above 1600 Years ſince in the Spirit
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49932:5"/>
and in the Truth, for the true Worſhippers to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in, in whom God ſeeks this <hi>Worſhip;</hi> I ſay, it is an Infallible <hi>Worſhip,</hi> or an Eternal <hi>Worſhip,</hi> for the Truth is Infallible, and the Spirit of God is Infallible and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, in which they worſhip the Eternal God and Truth, and the Spirit of God changes not, though Men may change from it; for the Truth makes no <hi>Sects</hi> nor <hi>Schiſms,</hi> for all <hi>Sests</hi> and <hi>Schiſmes</hi> be out of it; and the Spirit of God makes no <hi>Sects</hi> nor <hi>Schiſmes,</hi> for all <hi>Sects</hi> are out of the Spirit of God and out of Truth; for the Dragon, and the Devil, and the Deſtroyer, and the Beaſt are out of Truth, and his VVorſhippers, and the VVill-worſhippers; for the Devil abode not in the Truth, and all they that worſhip they don't know what, be out of the Truth and the Spirit of God: So had all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> kept to the Spirit and the Truth, that the Apoſtles and primitive Church was in, they would have kept up Chriſt's <hi>Worſhip,</hi> (and in it, as the Apoſtles did) that he ſet up above 1600 Years ſince, and there would have been no <hi>Sect</hi> among them, but they would have kept in the ſubſtantial <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;</hi> for Truth is ſubſtantial, and Truth doth not change, and the Spirit of God doth not change, but brings Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be Subſtantial in the Subſtantial <hi>Worſhip,</hi> and in the Spirit they would have had a Fellowſhip and a Unity. Therefore for all People to come out of the <hi>Sectary Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips,</hi> and <hi>Will-Worſhips,</hi> and worſhipping of Angells, worſhipping they don't know what; and to be the and true <hi>Worſhippers</hi> whom God ſeeks, they muſt all eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man and Woman come to Truth and the Spirit of God in their own Hearts, by which they may worſhip God in the Spirit &amp; Truth, which the Devil is out of, and to be the ſubſtantial <hi>Worſhippers</hi> that Chriſt ſet up above 1600 Years ſince; for all that do not worſhip God in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49932:5"/>
the Spirit and Truth, be in the falſe Spirit, and all that do not worſhip God in the Truth, they be out of the Truth, and of him that is out of the Truth; for Chriſt Jeſus, that ſignifies a Saviour and anointed of God, who came to redeem man from Iniquity, and ſave Man from Sin, and finiſhes Tranſgreſſion, and to be Man and Woman's Mediator, and to purchaſe man from Tranſgreſſion; and ſhed his Blood, and dyed for Man, who bruiſes the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents Head that has kept man in Captivity, and leads him Captive, and ſets man free from his Priſon, Death, Darkneſs and Bondage, who is out of Truth; and ſo Chriſt the Truth ſets up a Worſhip for Man and Woman in the Truth and in the Spirit that the Devil is out of; and this, I ſay, is the ſubſtantial Worſhip, where the Devil cannot come with his falſe, lying, murdering Spirit of Error, he cannot come into the Truth, nor into the Spirit of God. In which Truth and Spirit the true Worſhipers worſhip the God of all Truth in, who is a Spirit; and this I ſay is the true, and ſafe, and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, and infallible Worſhip that Chriſt ſet up, who is the Truth and a Quickening Spirit above 1600 Years ſince, and in which Worſhip there is neither <hi>Sect</hi> nor <hi>Schiſm</hi> nor Diſcord, for all that is out of Truth; for Concord is in the Spirit &amp; in the Truth, for the Unity &amp; the Fellowſhip is in the Spirit, and its called the Bond of Peace, and in this Spirit and Truth they muſt worſhip the God of Truth, who is a Spirit; ſo the blind <hi>Jews</hi> with the <hi>Scribes, Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> that think to go to worſhip at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Chriſt tells your Fore-Fathers above 1600 Years ſince, that God was not worſhipt there, nor at the Mountain; and therefore you are to believe in him your Saviour, and own his Worſhip in the Spirit and Truth: Now if all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> have the Scriptures of the New-Teſtament,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49932:6"/>
as the <hi>Jews</hi> had the Old, and do not worſhip God in the Spirit and in the Truth, which the Devil is out of, but make Worſhips of their own, and force men to them, they worſhip they do not know what; for it was the Dragon and the Beaſt that perſecuted about VVorſhip, both in the <hi>Jews</hi> in the Dayes of Chriſt in the Fleſh, and ſince in the Dayes of his Spiritual Appearance by the Holy Ghoſt, ſuch as were out of the Spirit of <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; the <hi>Prophets,</hi> &amp; <hi>Chriſt,</hi> &amp; his <hi>Apoſtles:</hi> So as the outward <hi>Jews</hi> were to go to outward <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to worſhip yearly, or elſe their Eyes were to rot in their Heads, and their Tongues in their Mouthes, and God's Plagues and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were to come upon them; ſo all they that are not in the Spirit, and are not in the Truth, by which they muſt worſhip the God of Truth, who is a Spirit, and ſo come to Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that is from above, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all true <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> I ſay, that Eye that is out of the Truth, and out of the Spirit, is under a Plague, and ſhall rot in their Heads and their Mouthes; for all the <hi>Jews</hi> in the Spirit and Truth in their Inward Parts, that worſhip God in the Spirit and Truth, that are the true VVorſhippers that God doth ſeek to worſhip him, and now God has found many, praiſed be his Name for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; I ſay, they do come to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that is above, the Mother of us all that are the true VVorſhippers, and do ſee <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that is below in Bondage with her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Now all People being dead in <hi>Adam,</hi> and gone aſtray, <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile;</hi> and Chriſt the Seeds-Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come, which ſows his ſeed upon all Grounds, and is come to make them to ſee, that did not ſee; and to make them blind that ſaid they ſaw, and ſaw not, as there is too many now a dayes; and his Grace hath appeared unto all Men, and hath enlightened all, and taſted Death
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49932:6"/>
for all, &amp; the Manifeſtation of his Spirit is given to every man to profit withall; ſo here Chriſt hath made no <hi>Sects,</hi> but they are the <hi>Sect-makers</hi> that goes from his true Light; and goes from his Word and Seed, and goes from the Manifeſtation of his Spirit that is given to every man to profit withall; and Chriſt has given to every man a Meaſure according to his Ability, and ſo they that go from their Meaſure that Chriſt has given unto them, are the <hi>Sect-makers,</hi> and are in the <hi>Schiſmes,</hi> then they may ſay that they have not Ability; but they have Ability to do Evil, it ſeems, and therefore theſe are they that turn againſt the true Worſhippers; therefore every Man and Woman that are the true Believers in Chriſt Jeſus the Saviour, they come to their meaſure that Chriſt has given them, the Light and Seed that Chriſt has ſown in their Field, their Hearts, and to the Holy-Ghoſt that does reprove them, and the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of the Spirit of God given to them to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit withall, which if they be the true Worſhippers in the Spirit and Truth, and comes out of the <hi>Sects,</hi> and give over making <hi>Sects.</hi> Then there would be no <hi>Sect</hi> in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> nor in the World, nor among the <hi>Jews,</hi> if they all would come to the Truth in their Inward Parts, to the Spirit of God within, and in that Spirit and Truth to worſhip God, who is a Spirit, and who is the Truth, then they would worſhip in that which the Devil can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come, for he is out of the Truth; ſo I ſay, if all People in the whole World would come into the Spirit, and come into the Truth, in which they are to worſhip the God of Truth, they would be all in Unity in the Truth and in the Spirit; ſo as all People have been in the Deceit and Falſhood, out of the Truth, and in the Falſe Spirit, out of the true; ſo muſt all People Men
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49932:7"/>
and Women come into the true, out of the falſe Spirit, and come into Truth out of the falſe and Deceit, if they be the true Worſhippers that worſhip God in the Spirit and in the Truth, for ſuch he ſeeks to worſhip him; for this, as I ſaid before, is the ſubſtantial Worſhip, that Chriſt ſet up for his redeemed ones, and ſaved ones that had been under the Power of Satan, and his falſe Spirit, who had been deceived by him who abode not in the Truth; therefore Chriſt the Saviour and Redeemer, who is the Truth, that bruiſes the Head of the Serpent, ſets up a Worſhip in the Spirit and Truth, which the Devil is out of; and this is the Perfect and Subſtantial VVorſhip; for Truth is Perfect, and will ſtand, and the Spirit of God, which the true VVorſhippers in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and the Truth worſhip in; I ſay, this Worſhip in the Spirit and the Truth will ſtand, when all the VVorſhips out of the Spirit and Truth are gone, which Chriſt the Son of God, the Truth which came from God, ſet up above 1600 Years ſince. Bleſſed and praiſed be God through him for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Kingſton,</hi> 
                  <date>the 9th of the 8th Moneth <hi>1673.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>G. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49932:7"/>
            <p>ALL the Worſhips that have been made by man, and ſet up by man, and compelled thereto by man in the world ſince Chriſt hath ſet up his Worſhip in the Spirit and in the Truth, above 1600 years ſince, to worſhip God who is a Spirit, to worſhip him in the Spirit and Truth, which he ſeeks and who are the true VVorſhippers, they are like, and from the ſame Spirit that ſet up Worſhips before Chriſt came in the Fleſh, who had not the Spirit of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, as theſe now ſay they have, nor the Spirit and Power the Apoſtles had, and yet they perſecute them that are in the Spirit of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets; and all theſe ſay now that have made VVorſhips, and ſet them up, and compelled and perſecuted others for not conforming, and put them to Death: I ſay, they ſay and confeſs they have not the ſame Power and Spirit the Apoſtles had; therefore they be in another Power, and another Spirit, and an unclean Ghoſt, and compel people to it; for there is but one ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt that leads into all Truth, and one Spirit that Baptiſeth into one Body, and the Power of God, and the power of Satan, and one Truth, which the Devil is out of; ſo all that worſhip the God of Truth, muſt be in the Spirit of God, and be in the Truth the Devil is out of; and theſe be the true VVorſhippers of the God of Truth, who is a Spirit, and this Truth and Spirit is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, and they in it; and they are all falſe VVor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers that be out of Truth, and out of Gods Spirit, and they worſhip the VVorks of their own hands, and they don't know what; and all that have not, and are not in the ſame Power, Spirit and holy Ghoſt that the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49932:8"/>
Apoſtles were in, and the ſame Truth, you are not the true VVorſhippers, though you may talk of all the words of the Scriptures of Truth, and give your mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and ſell them for ſo much a year, and make Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of them, and Prayers of them, and Songs of them; yet, I ſay, if you be not in the ſame Spirit and Power that they were in, the Prophets and Apoſtles that gave them forth, and have not the Spirit of Chriſt in you, you are none of Chriſts, nor none of his true Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, that worſhip God in the Spirit and in the Truth, as the Apoſtles did, but you are like unto all other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional worſhips, and the Jews that oppoſed Chriſt the Truth and Spirit, and the ſpiritual Man, and ſo his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual worſhip in Truth, and his true Worſhippers, as ſufficiently hath been ſeen; and ſo all the Worſhippers that be out of the Spirit of God &amp; his Truth, are as I ſaid before, like unto thoſe Worſhippers before Chriſt came in the Fleſh, that perſecuted the Prophets, and perſecuted Chriſt in the Fleſh above 1600 years ſince, and his Apoſtles, and now he perſecutes in the Spirit; and ſuch may pretend to worſhip God like the Jews, but grieve, and quench, and vex the Spirit of God, and walk con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Truth in themſelves, and ſuch will never come to be the true Worſhippers that Chriſt the Truth ſet up, in the Spirit and in the Truth that the Devil is out of, that God who is a Spirit ſeeks to worſhip him, until they come to the Spirit and Truth, and walk in it in their own particulars; and ſo all the true Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, that come out of the falſe Worſhips, that worſhip they don't know what, they muſt be in the Power, and the Spirit, and the holy Ghoſt that the Apoſtles were in, who worſhip God in the Spirit and in the Truth that doth not change, for Truth doth not change, though
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49932:8"/>
men have changed from it, and the Worſhip that Chriſt hath ſet up in it; and the Spirit of God doth not Change, though men and women have changed, and erred from it, and gone into ſo many Sects and Worſhips, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute one another about them; and God doth not change, nor his Worſhip in the Spirit and Truth which the Devil is out of; God's worſhip which Chriſt ſet up doth not change, nor Chriſt doth not change, nor God doth not change, who is to be worſhipped in Spirit and Truth that doth not change, and this is the Safe, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and Infallible, Catholick or Univerſal Worſhip; for Truth and the Spirit of God is perfect; ſo men and women muſt worſhip in that which is perfect: God who is perfect, and Chriſt who is perfect ſet up this his perfect Worſhip above 1600 years ſince; and men are gone out of his Worſhip, and gone into imperfect Worſhips; ſo every man and woman muſt come to the Meaſure of the perfect Spirit and Truth in their own hearts, if they be the true Worſhippers of God in the Spirit and Truth, and with the Spirit, and with the Truth within they muſt feel the God of Truth who is a Spirit, at hand, with them, and Chriſt the Truth, that ſet up this Worſhip, as I ſaid before, above ſixteen hundred years ſince in the Spirit and in the Truth, and they that be in the Spirit and in the Truth are the true Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and can ſay, the Lord has ſought them, and the Lord has found them to worſhip him in his Spirit, and in the Truth, that the Devil is out of, and can praiſe God through Jeſus Chriſt, whom God ſent above 1600 Years ſince, to ſet them up this Worſhip; for Chriſt, that is the Saviour and Redeemer from Sin and Iniquity, ſet up an eſtabliſhed Worſhip in the Spirit and in the Truth, which the Devil is out of, by which Truth, Men and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49932:9"/>
Women are made free, they are God's Free-men and Free-women, that are made free by the Truth, and ſerves and worſhips God in the Spirit and in the Truth, that makes them free, which is our eſtabliſhed Worſhip, which is ſet over the Head of the Serpent, and the Heads of the Beaſt, and the Whore that abides not in her houſe, and the Head of the Serpent, which is out of Truth, and over his Power, is the Truth, in which Spirit and Truth all the true Worſhippers worſhip God; ſo as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>If the Truth hath made you free, then are you free indeed;</hi> for all Captivity, Thraldom, Bondage and Slavery is out of Truth, and under the Head of the Serpent, whoſe Head Chriſt the Truth bruiſes; ſo the true Worſhippers worſhip God in the Spirit and in the Truth, which makes them free, and can praiſe God through Jeſus Chriſt for his Worſhip, and for their Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom through him, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. F.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49932:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
